<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pengkuang.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://pengkuang.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-04-19T09:22:46+00:00</updated><id>https://pengkuang.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">a post with plotly.js</title><link href="https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2025/plotly/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with plotly.js"/><published>2025-03-26T14:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-26T14:24:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2025/plotly</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2025/plotly/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with some <a href="https://plotly.com/javascript/">plotly</a> code.</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">plotly
</span><span class="sb">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [10, 15, 13, 17],
      "type": "scatter"
    },
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [16, 5, 11, 9],
      "type": "scatter"
    }
  ]
}</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Which generates:</p> <pre><code class="language-plotly">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [10, 15, 13, 17],
      "type": "scatter"
    },
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [16, 5, 11, 9],
      "type": "scatter"
    }
  ]
}
</code></pre> <p>Also another example chart.</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">plotly
</span><span class="sb">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [10, 15, 13, 17],
      "mode": "markers"
    },
    {
      "x": [2, 3, 4, 5],
      "y": [16, 5, 11, 9],
      "mode": "lines"
    },
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [12, 9, 15, 12],
      "mode": "lines+markers"
    }
  ],
  "layout": {
    "title": {
      "text": "Line and Scatter Plot"
    }
  }
}</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This is how it looks like:</p> <pre><code class="language-plotly">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [10, 15, 13, 17],
      "mode": "markers"
    },
    {
      "x": [2, 3, 4, 5],
      "y": [16, 5, 11, 9],
      "mode": "lines"
    },
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [12, 9, 15, 12],
      "mode": "lines+markers"
    }
  ],
  "layout": {
    "title": {
      "text": "Line and Scatter Plot"
    }
  }
}
</code></pre>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="charts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included plotly.js code could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with image galleries</title><link href="https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2024/photo-gallery/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with image galleries"/><published>2024-12-04T01:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-04T01:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2024/photo-gallery</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2024/photo-gallery/"><![CDATA[<p>The images in this post are all zoomable, arranged into different mini-galleries using different libraries.</p> <h2 id="lightbox2"><a href="https://lokeshdhakar.com/projects/lightbox2/">Lightbox2</a></h2> <p><a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-2500.jpg" data-lightbox="roadtrip"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-200.jpg"/></a> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-2500.jpg" data-lightbox="roadtrip"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-200.jpg"/></a> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-2500.jpg" data-lightbox="roadtrip"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-200.jpg"/></a></p> <hr/> <h2 id="photoswipe"><a href="https://photoswipe.com/">PhotoSwipe</a></h2> <div class="pswp-gallery pswp-gallery--single-column" id="gallery--getting-started"> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-2500.jpg" data-pswp-width="1669" data-pswp-height="2500" target="_blank"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-200.jpg" alt=""/> </a> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/7/img-2500.jpg" data-pswp-width="1875" data-pswp-height="2500" data-cropped="true" target="_blank"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/7/img-200.jpg" alt=""/> </a> <a href="https://unsplash.com" data-pswp-src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-2500.jpg" data-pswp-width="2500" data-pswp-height="1666" target="_blank"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-200.jpg" alt=""/> </a> <div> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/6/img-2500.jpg" data-pswp-width="2500" data-pswp-height="1667" target="_blank"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/6/img-200.jpg" alt=""/> </a> </div> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="spotlight-js"><a href="https://nextapps-de.github.io/spotlight/">Spotlight JS</a></h2> <div class="spotlight-group"> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-200.jpg"/> </a> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-200.jpg"/> </a> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-200.jpg"/> </a> </div> <div class="spotlight-group"> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/4/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/4/img-200.jpg"/> </a> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/5/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/5/img-200.jpg"/> </a> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/6/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/6/img-200.jpg"/> </a> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="venobox"><a href="https://veno.es/venobox/">Venobox</a></h2> <p><a class="venobox" data-gall="myGallery" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-2500.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-200.jpg"/></a> <a class="venobox" data-gall="myGallery" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-2500.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-200.jpg"/></a> <a class="venobox" data-gall="myGallery" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-2500.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-200.jpg"/></a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="images"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included image galleries could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra</title><link href="https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra"/><published>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/"><![CDATA[<p>May 14, 2024[[read-time]] min read We’re introducing a series of updates across the Gemini family of models, including the new 1.5 Flash, our lightweight model for speed and efficiency, and Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants. In December, we launched our first natively multimodal model Gemini 1.0 in three sizes: Ultra, Pro and Nano. Just a few months later we released 1.5 Pro, with enhanced performance and a breakthrough long context window of 1 million tokens.Developers and enterprise customers have been putting 1.5 Pro to use in incredible ways and finding its long context window, multimodal reasoning capabilities and impressive overall performance incredibly useful.We know from user feedback that some applications need lower latency and a lower cost to serve. This inspired us to keep innovating, so today, we’re introducing Gemini 1.5 Flash: a model that’s lighter-weight than 1.5 Pro, and designed to be fast and efficient to serve at scale.Both 1.5 Pro and 1.5 Flash are available in public preview with a 1 million token context window in Google AI Studio and Vertex AI. And now, 1.5 Pro is also available with a 2 million token context window via waitlist to developers using the API and to Google Cloud customers.We’re also introducing updates across the Gemini family of models, announcing our next generation of open models, Gemma 2, and sharing progress on the future of AI assistants, with Project Astra.Context lengths of leading foundation models compared with Gemini 1.5’s 2 million token capability1.5 Flash is the newest addition to the Gemini model family and the fastest Gemini model served in the API. It’s optimized for high-volume, high-frequency tasks at scale, is more cost-efficient to serve and features our breakthrough long context window.While it’s a lighter weight model than 1.5 Pro, it’s highly capable of multimodal reasoning across vast amounts of information and delivers impressive quality for its size.The new Gemini 1.5 Flash model is optimized for speed and efficiency, is highly capable of multimodal reasoning and features our breakthrough long context window.1.5 Flash excels at summarization, chat applications, image and video captioning, data extraction from long documents and tables, and more. This is because it’s been trained by 1.5 Pro through a process called “distillation,” where the most essential knowledge and skills from a larger model are transferred to a smaller, more efficient model.Read more about 1.5 Flash in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report, on the Gemini technology page, and learn about 1.5 Flash’s availability and pricing.Over the last few months, we’ve significantly improved 1.5 Pro, our best model for general performance across a wide range of tasks.Beyond extending its context window to 2 million tokens, we’ve enhanced its code generation, logical reasoning and planning, multi-turn conversation, and audio and image understanding through data and algorithmic advances. We see strong improvements on public and internal benchmarks for each of these tasks.1.5 Pro can now follow increasingly complex and nuanced instructions, including ones that specify product-level behavior involving role, format and style. We’ve improved control over the model’s responses for specific use cases, like crafting the persona and response style of a chat agent or automating workflows through multiple function calls. And we’ve enabled users to steer model behavior by setting system instructions.We added audio understanding in the Gemini API and Google AI Studio, so 1.5 Pro can now reason across image and audio for videos uploaded in Google AI Studio. And we’re now integrating 1.5 Pro into Google products, including Gemini Advanced and in Workspace apps.Read more about 1.5 Pro in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report and on the Gemini technology page.Gemini Nano is expanding beyond text-only inputs to include images as well. Starting with Pixel, applications using Gemini Nano with Multimodality will be able to understand the world the way people do — not just through text, but also through sight, sound and spoken language.Read more about Gemini 1.0 Nano on Android.Today, we’re also sharing a series of updates to Gemma, our family of open models built from the same research and technology used to create the Gemini models.We’re announcing Gemma 2, our next generation of open models for responsible AI innovation. Gemma 2 has a new architecture designed for breakthrough performance and efficiency, and will be available in new sizes.The Gemma family is also expanding with PaliGemma, our first vision-language model inspired by PaLI-3. And we’ve upgraded our Responsible Generative AI Toolkit with LLM Comparator for evaluating the quality of model responses.Read more on the Developer blog.As part of Google DeepMind’s mission to build AI responsibly to benefit humanity, we’ve always wanted to develop universal AI agents that can be helpful in everyday life. That’s why today, we’re sharing our progress in building the future of AI assistants with Project Astra (advanced seeing and talking responsive agent).To be truly useful, an agent needs to understand and respond to the complex and dynamic world just like people do — and take in and remember what it sees and hears to understand context and take action. It also needs to be proactive, teachable and personal, so users can talk to it naturally and without lag or delay.While we’ve made incredible progress developing AI systems that can understand multimodal information, getting response time down to something conversational is a difficult engineering challenge. Over the past few years, we’ve been working to improve how our models perceive, reason and converse to make the pace and quality of interaction feel more natural.Building on Gemini, we’ve developed prototype agents that can process information faster by continuously encoding video frames, combining the video and speech input into a timeline of events, and caching this information for efficient recall.By leveraging our leading speech models, we also enhanced how they sound, giving the agents a wider range of intonations. These agents can better understand the context they’re being used in, and respond quickly, in conversation.With technology like this, it’s easy to envision a future where people could have an expert AI assistant by their side, through a phone or glasses. And some of these capabilities are coming to Google products, like the Gemini app and web experience, later this year.We’ve made incredible progress so far with our family of Gemini models, and we’re always striving to advance the state-of-the-art even further. By investing in a relentless production line of innovation, we’re able to explore new ideas at the frontier, while also unlocking the possibility of new and exciting Gemini use cases.Learn more about Gemini and its capabilities. Your information will be used in accordance with Google’s privacy policy.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>      Done. Just one step more.
    
      Check your inbox to confirm your subscription.
    You are already subscribed to our newsletter.
    You can also subscribe with a
    different email address
    
    .
    
  Let’s stay in touch. Get the latest news from Google in your inbox.
          Follow Us
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re sharing updates across our Gemini family of models and a glimpse of Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with tabs</title><link href="https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2024/tabs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with tabs"/><published>2024-05-01T00:32:13+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-01T00:32:13+00:00</updated><id>https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2024/tabs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2024/tabs/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://web-api.textin.com/ocr_image/external/bb3c5c944b1aa20d.jpg" alt=""/></p> <h1 id="can-we-make-reading-code-easier-with-eye-tracking">Can we make reading code easier with eye tracking?</h1> <p>(10 minute read)</p> <h1 id="peng-kuang">Peng Kuang</h1> <p>Reading code is time-consuming for software engineers and therefore costs a lot of money. A study at Lund University is investigating technologies to shorten the time needed for it. Eye tracking is one of the solutions that hopefully can achieve that.</p> <h1 id="what-is-code">What is Code?</h1> <p>Code is the instructions that we use to communicate with a computer. We can write code in different programming languages such as C++, Java, and Python. A simple but commonly used code example for teaching the syntax (the way words can be arranged to formulate language structures) to beginners in almost every programming language is such a one-line statement:</p> <p>System.out.print(“Hello World!”);</p> <p>** This example statement is written in Java. It tells the computer to print out “Hello World!”. When it is written in other programming languages, the syntax can be slightly or largely different depending on the programming language you choose.</p> <p>Similar to how we compose texts in natural languages, code can be written as short or long. It can be as short as just one sentence. It can also be as long as millions of lines. The latter case normally occurs when we are developing large-scale software. The software essentially is a container of code. Large-scale software is just the type of software that contains more code, like a thick textbook containing millions of lines of text.</p> <p>Why can code be difficult to understand?</p> <p>In general, code is deemed difficult to understand. On the high level, the reason is twofold. Intrinsically, the syntax can be cognitively demanding to understand sometimes, especially if the programming language is poorly designed. Extrinsically, as the volume of code increases, so does its complexity. Therefore, it requires more cognitive effort to make sense of it. This is pronounced when the code is poorly written. For instance, the code style is inconsistent (software development usually involves many programmers writing different parts of the code nowadays), and/or the architecture is not well-designed such that different parts of code are entangled like spaghetti. Anecdotally, spaghetti code are not uncommon in the industry as businesses tend to prioritize delivery over perfect code.</p> <p><img src="https://web-api.textin.com/ocr_image/external/ef408b58cda90ef3.jpg" alt=""/></p> <p>An example of Spaghetti code.</p> <h1 id="why-is-it-important-to-make-it-easier">Why is it important to make it easier?</h1> <p>Many tools have been developed to mitigate the impact of these two factors, but still, it consumes a lot of programmers’ time to read and understand code. For example, Google reports that new software engineers at the company may take 12-21 weeks to get familiar with the codebase of a project. This implies that precious software engineer time is being invested in this. Moreover, many software engineers do not enjoy doing this task.</p> <h1 id="how-can-we-make-it-easier">How can we make it easier?</h1> <p>In our study, we deal with the presentation layer of the problem. That is, to focus on reducing programmers’ time spent navigating to the files (similar to the pages of a book) and searching for the relevant lines of code when working on a large codebase. Our approach does not care much about how the code functions.</p> <p><img src="https://web-api.textin.com/ocr_image/external/04c2a6cbd2c6e41c.jpg" alt=""/></p> <p>The components inside a typical eye tracker.</p> <h1 id="why-eye-tracking">Why eye tracking?</h1> <p>For this purpose, we make use of eye tracking. Eye tracking is an unintrusive technology that captures a user’s eye movement with infrared light and a camera. With algorithms, it can calculate where the user’s gaze was on a stimulus such as a code snippet.</p> <p>Diving into such data, we can tell where programmers’ attention was distributed among the lines of a code file or the code files of a software project. If we visualize the attention distribution properly, programmers can follow these visual cues and only spend time reading the most relevant parts of code or code files. Additionally, we can measure the individual attention of a programmer and compare it with the summed attention of an entire developer team. The deviation derived from such comparison can inform the programmers of where they missed reading or can potentially spend more time, for example, when they are looking for errors in the code.</p> <h1 id="who-will-benefit-from-such-support">Who will benefit from such support?</h1> <p>Providing such on-demand support may boost software engineers’ efficiency in reading and understanding a codebase and thus their productivity. Other cohorts of programmers can benefit from such gaze-based assistance too. For example, programming learners who often work on pre-scaffolded assignment projects, professional developer wannabes who attempt to contribute to open-source projects to build a good portfolio, and programmers (e.g., neurodivergent programmers, programmers with low proficiency in English) who prefer a learning style that is not purely textual. As Large Language Models (LLMs) such as ChatGPT and Co-pilot have lowered the barrier to learning programming, new kinds of tool assistance, e.g., enabled by eye-tracking in our case, may empower a broader and more diverse population than ever before.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Fact Box</th> <th>Fact Box</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>Term</td> <td>Explanation</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Programming Languages</td> <td>A set of rules that a programmer can follow to compose instructions for a computer.</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Codebase</td> <td>A virtual space for storing all the code and other necessary files of a software project.</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Stimulus</td> <td>The material used in an eye-tracking experiment, e.g., an image or a code snippet.</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Gaze</td> <td>The output from an eye tracker. It describes the participant’s eye movement on a stimulus.</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Large Language Models (LLMs)</td> <td>A type of architecture that performs well in generating textual answers for questions in natural language.</td> </tr> <tr> <td>ChatGPT</td> <td>A platform enabled by an OpenAI-owned LLM where you can ask questions to get usually good answers.</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Co-pilot</td> <td>A similar product to ChatGPT that was released by Microsoft.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included tabs in a post could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with typograms</title><link href="https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2024/typograms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with typograms"/><published>2024-04-29T23:36:10+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-29T23:36:10+00:00</updated><id>https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2024/typograms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2024/typograms/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with some <a href="https://github.com/google/typograms/">typograms</a> code.</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">typograms
</span><span class="sb">+----+
|    |---&gt; My first diagram!
+----+</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Which generates:</p> <pre><code class="language-typograms">+----+
|    |---&gt; My first diagram!
+----+
</code></pre> <p>Another example:</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">typograms
</span><span class="sb">.------------------------.
|.----------------------.|
||"https://example.com" ||
|'----------------------'|
| ______________________ |
||                      ||
||   Welcome!           ||
||                      ||
||                      ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  | username       |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  |"*******"       |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||                      ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  |   "Sign-up"    |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||                      ||
|+----------------------+|
.------------------------.</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>which generates:</p> <pre><code class="language-typograms">.------------------------.
|.----------------------.|
||"https://example.com" ||
|'----------------------'|
| ______________________ |
||                      ||
||   Welcome!           ||
||                      ||
||                      ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  | username       |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  |"*******"       |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||                      ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  |   "Sign-up"    |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||                      ||
|+----------------------+|
.------------------------.
</code></pre> <p>For more examples, check out the <a href="https://google.github.io/typograms/#examples">typograms documentation</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="diagrams"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included typograms code could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can we make reading code easier with eye tracking?</title><link href="https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2024/post-citation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can we make reading code easier with eye tracking?"/><published>2024-04-28T15:06:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-28T15:06:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2024/post-citation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2024/post-citation/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/posts/cover-gaze.jpg" alt="gaze heatmap"/></p> <h1 id="can-we-make-reading-code-easier-with-eye-tracking">Can we make reading code easier with eye tracking?</h1> <p>(10 minute read)</p> <p>Peng Kuang</p> <p>Reading code is time-consuming for software engineers and therefore costs a lot of money. A study at Lund University is investigating technologies to shorten the time needed for it. Eye tracking is one of the solutions that hopefully can achieve that.</p> <h1 id="what-is-code">What is Code?</h1> <p>Code is the instructions that we use to communicate with a computer. We can write code in different programming languages such as C++, Java, and Python. A simple but commonly used code example for teaching the syntax (the way words can be arranged to formulate language structures) to beginners in almost every programming language is such a one-line statement:</p> <p>| System.out.print(“Hello World!”); <em>** This example statement is written in Java. It tells the computer to print out “Hello World!”. When it is written in other programming languages, the syntax can be slightly or largely different depending on the programming language you choose.</em> | | :—- |</p> <p>Similar to how we compose texts in natural languages, code can be written as short or long. It can be as short as just one sentence. It can also be as long as millions of lines. The latter case normally occurs when we are developing large-scale software. The software essentially is a container of code. Large-scale software is just the type of software that contains more code, like a thick textbook containing millions of lines of text.</p> <h1 id="why-can-code-be-difficult-to-understand">Why can code be difficult to understand?</h1> <p>In general, code is deemed difficult to understand. On the high level, the reason is twofold. Intrinsically, the syntax can be cognitively demanding to understand sometimes, especially if the programming language is poorly designed. Extrinsically, as the volume of code increases, so does its complexity. Therefore, it requires more cognitive effort to make sense of it. This is pronounced when the code is poorly written. For instance, the code style is inconsistent (software development usually involves many programmers writing different parts of the code nowadays), and/or the architecture is not well-designed such that different parts of code are entangled like spaghetti. Anecdotally, spaghetti code are not uncommon in the industry as businesses tend to prioritize delivery over perfect code.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/posts/spaghetti-code.png" alt="spaghetti code"/></p> <p>An example of Spaghetti code.</p> <h1 id="why-is-it-important-to-make-it-easier">Why is it important to make it easier?</h1> <p>Many tools have been developed to mitigate the impact of these two factors, but still, it consumes a lot of programmers’ time to read and understand code. For example, Google reports that new software engineers at the company may take 12-21 weeks to get familiar with the codebase of a project. This implies that precious software engineer time is being invested in this. Moreover, many software engineers do not enjoy doing this task.</p> <h1 id="how-can-we-make-it-easier">How can we make it easier?</h1> <p>In our study, we deal with the presentation layer of the problem. That is, to focus on reducing programmers’ time spent navigating to the files (similar to the pages of a book) and searching for the relevant lines of code when working on a large codebase. Our approach does not care much about how the code functions.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/posts/tobii-eye-tracker.png" alt="Tobii eye tracker"/></p> <p>The components inside a typical eye tracker.</p> <h1 id="why-eye-tracking">Why eye tracking?</h1> <p>For this purpose, we make use of eye tracking. Eye tracking is an unintrusive technology that captures a user’s eye movement with infrared light and a camera. With algorithms, it can calculate where the user’s gaze was on a stimulus such as a code snippet.</p> <p>Diving into such data, we can tell where programmers’ attention was distributed among the lines of a code file or the code files of a software project. If we visualize the attention distribution properly, programmers can follow these visual cues and only spend time reading the most relevant parts of code or code files. Additionally, we can measure the individual attention of a programmer and compare it with the summed attention of an entire developer team. The deviation derived from such comparison can inform the programmers of where they missed reading or can potentially spend more time, for example, when they are looking for errors in the code.</p> <h1 id="who-will-benefit-from-such-support">Who will benefit from such support?</h1> <p>Providing such on-demand support may boost software engineers’ efficiency in reading and understanding a codebase and thus their productivity. Other cohorts of programmers can benefit from such gaze-based assistance too. For example, programming learners who often work on pre-scaffolded assignment projects, professional developer wannabes who attempt to contribute to open-source projects to build a good portfolio, and programmers (e.g., neurodivergent programmers, programmers with low proficiency in English) who prefer a learning style that is not purely textual. As Large Language Models (LLMs) such as ChatGPT and Co-pilot have lowered the barrier to learning programming, new kinds of tool assistance, e.g., enabled by eye-tracking in our case, may empower a broader and more diverse population than ever before.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Fact Box</th> <th style="text-align: left"> </th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>Term</strong></td> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Explanation</strong></td> </tr> <tr> <td>Programming Languages</td> <td style="text-align: left">A set of rules that a programmer can follow to compose instructions for a computer.</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Codebase</td> <td style="text-align: left">A virtual space for storing all the code and other necessary files of a software project.</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Stimulus</td> <td style="text-align: left">The material used in an eye-tracking experiment, e.g., an image or a code snippet.</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Gaze</td> <td style="text-align: left">The output from an eye tracker. It describes the participant’s eye movement on a stimulus.</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Large Language Models (LLMs)</td> <td style="text-align: left">A type of architecture that performs well in generating textual answers for questions in natural language.</td> </tr> <tr> <td>ChatGPT</td> <td style="text-align: left">A platform enabled by an OpenAI-owned LLM where you can ask questions to get usually good answers.</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Co-pilot</td> <td style="text-align: left">A similar product to ChatGPT that was released by Microsoft.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="work"/><category term="popular"/><category term="science"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[popular science style article]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pengkuang.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[<h3>External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</h3> <p>If you prefer publishing blog posts on medium.com or other external sources, starting version v0.5.0, <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio">al-folio</a> lets you to display your external posts in the blog feed of your website! 🎉🎉</p> <p>Configuring external sources of super simple. After upgrading to v0.5.0, just add the following section to your _config.yml:</p> <pre>external_sources:<br />  - name: medium.com  # name of the source (arbitrary string)<br />    rss_url: <a href="https://medium.com/@al-folio/feed">https://medium.com/@&lt;your-medium-username&gt;/feed</a></pre> <p>The example above adds your medium.com blog post feed as an external source. But you can add arbitrary RSS feeds as sources.</p> <p>Any questions or suggestions? 👉 Start <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio/discussions">a discussion on GitHub</a>!</p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=b60a1d241a0a" width="1" height="1" alt=""/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>